THEDA U. P. BARTOLOMAEUS

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER

Bouchestraße 19 12435 Berlin +49 157 71425088 th.bartolomaeus@gmail.com orcid id 0000-0002-5156-7184

RESEARCH INTEREST

I am a full-stack systems biologist with profound practical experience in both wet lab platforms and bioinformatics, with a special interest in the effects of climate change on environmental microbiomes. I am also very passionate about science communication and public engagement.

SKILLS

Wet Lab (metagenomic sample collection/ processing, qPCR, flowcytometry, 16S processing, animal work)

Dry Lab (data integration, statistical analysis, and data visualization in R, network cooccurrence analysis, longitudinal modeling, confounder analysis, machine learning)

Grant writing, project development and research collaborations (DAAD, DFG)

Science communication and supervision of Bachelor & Master students

EDUCATION

DOCTORAL STUDIES

Experimental and Clinical Research Center a joint venture of Max Delbrück Center for Moleculare Medicine and Charité Univeritätsmedizin Berlin

since 07/2019

Submitted in September 2023

Defended 18th of October 2024

Thesis project: Technical confounders in microbiome studies – examples from fecal and sputum microbiome research. Minimizing potential technical biases and facilitating clinical studies by developing new methods and tools.

Supervisors: Dr. Sofia K. Forslund-Startceva, Dr. PD Enno Klussmann, Dr. Lajos Markó

DIPLOM LEBENSMITTELCHEMIE STUDIES

10/2014 - 07/2019

08/2011 - 06/2013

Technische Universität Berlin, Berlin, Germany

Thesis: Comparison of Different Methods for the Analysis of Gut Microbiome Composition **Appraised**: Prof. Dr. Hajo Haase

STATE-CERTIFIED TECHNICAL ASSISTANT FOR CHEMICAL AND BIOLOGICAL LABORATORIES

Lette Verein (Berufsausbildungszentrum, Stiftung des öffentlichen Rechts), Berlin, Germany

CAREER HISTORY

RESEARCHER

AG Müller/Dechend since 07/2024

Experimental and Clinical Research Center a joint venture of Max Delbrück Center for Moleculare Medicine and Charité Univeritätsmedizin Berlin

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

AG Forslund

Experimental and Clinical Research Center a joint venture of Max Delbrück Center for Moleculare Medicine and Charité Univeritätsmedizin Berlin

TECHNICAL ASSISTANT

07/2013-09/2014

since 07/2019

Bilacon GmbH, Berlin, Germany

INTERNSHIP 01/2013-04/2013

Station biologique de Concarneau, Concarneau, France Phylogenetic analysis of fish species (Leonardo da Vinci Program der EU)

,

THIRD PARTY FUNDING

VasBio - Biomarkers for Vascular Phenotypes since

CALL

since 09/2024

71.100 Euro

FIRST TRANSLATIONAL STUDY CALL CLINICAL RESEARCH UNIT (CRU)

since 07/2019

50.000 Euro